Guide to the Ezra Cornell Papers, 1746-1888
Cornell, Ezra Papers, 1746-1888
- Series I. Correspondence 1746-1878
  - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence
    - Correspondence :: Ezra Cornell Correspondence :: 1851-1856
      - April 1, 1853 - April 25, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 2)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, consolidation of lines, transfer of lines, patents and contracts, western lines; Ithaca land.
        April 24, 1853. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "The history of Telegraph has therefor been a history of wars, and there are many of those contests unsettled?"
        Fall Creek.
        Wood, Phebe; Smith, F.O.J.; Kendall, Amos; O'Reilly, Henry; Delano, W.J.; Wood, M.B.; Morse, Samuel F.B.
      - April 26, 1853 - May 18, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 3)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, consolidation of lines, transfer of lines, patents and contracts, western lines.
        Indiana; Montreal; Chicago; Fall Creek.
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Wood, O.S.; Chester, E.W.
      - May 20, 1853 - July 4, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 4)
        Indiana.
        O'Reilly, Henry; Chester, E.W.; Speed, C.H.
      - July 15, 1853 - July 31, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 5)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines, materials and supplies.
        July 21, 1853. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell from Chicago:
        "There are some six hundred to a thousand Odd Fellows in the city from other parts of the state and they are having a celebration - a procession this P.M."
        Indiana; Indianapolis.
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Speed, C.H.; Chester, E.W.
      - August 1, 1853 - August 16, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 6)
        Speed, C.H.; Speed, J.J.
      - August 20, 1853 - September 8, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 7)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines, materials and supplies, transfer of lines, consolidation of lines; account of a family trip west; Ithaca land.
      - September 10, 1853 - September 26, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 8)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations; Ithaca land; extracts and transcripts of F.O.J. Smith letters.
        September 19, 1853. D.B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "I?write again to ask what kind of employment you could give me and where would it and so forth if I should abandon the Idea of going to the gold diggins. My mind has been so unsettled since Maria's Death that I could hardly tell what I was going to do."
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Speed, J.J.; Cornell, D.B.; Smith, F.O.J.
      - September 27, 1853 - October 13, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 9)
        Gordon, D.P.
      - October 15, 1853 - October 31, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 10)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines.
        Indiana; Ohio; Ithaca.
      - November 1, 1853 - November 16, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 11)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines, consolidation of lines, transfer of lines; Union Telegraph, Speed and O'Reilly Lines.
        November 5, 1853. J.J. Speed to Ezra Cornell:
        "I think it probable that O'R has got [?] & may give us some trouble, in consequence of not carrying out his darling project of a grand consolidated Company, making him Pres't with a salary of five thousand dollars."
        Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Kendall, Amos.
      - November 17, 1853 - December 5, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 12)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines, consolidation of lines.
        December 1, 1853. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "This is destined to be a great city. Chicago has now a population of over 50 thousand population and this will double and quadruple as rapedly as that of any other city of the union."
        Chicago.
        Cornell, Mary Ann.
      - December 6, 1853 - December 20, 1853 (Box 14, Folder 13)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines; American Telegraph Confederation.
        December 6, 1853. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "I have had some tooth ache this P.M. in an old snag that was left some ten years ago, when I went to Ithaca at midnight with Dennis McCoy the Irishman to hold my head. You may recollect the history of that terable night. Dr Miles (I think) pulled on it 3 times with his entire strength, and as offin the irons broke loos. The fourth pull broke the tooth taking the tooth with one prong out, and a piece of the jaw with it."
        Bristol, John S.; Cornell, Mary Ann.
      - December 22, 1853 - January 12, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 1)
        January 5, 1854. describing a train trip to the west:
        "I received an invitation from Mr. Tubbs to go to the 'Grand Concert of Madame Sontag' who was to appear for the first time on the Cleveland 'boards' -- I accepted, the house was crowded, and the audience have marked evidence of their satisfaction. The pieces were Italian and French excepting 'Home Sweet Home' which was so distorted by artistic skill that it made me nervous."
        Ezra Cornell's account of the origins of the Cornell-Speed partnership in the telegraph business.
        January 8, 1854. Mary Ann Cornell to Ezra Cornell recounting her trip via steamer and stage to Syracuse for a wedding.
        Ithaca; Chicago; Fall Creek; Indiana.
        Delano, W.J.; O'Reilly, Henry; Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, Alonzo B.
      - January 14, 1854 - January 26, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 2)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines; smallpox.
        Indiana; Ohio.
        Cornell, E.B.; O'Reilly, Henry; Cornell, E.S.
      - January 27, 1854 - February 20, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 3)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines, adjudication of telegraph disputes, transfer of patents; smallpox; American Telegraph Confederation.
        January 27, 1854. Mary C. Robertson to Ezra Cornell:
        "Jane says Brother E.B. is in the lottery business some this winter which surprises me very much. I don't know but its honorable business in N.Y. State."
        Robertson, Mary C.; Wood, M.B.; Morse, Samuel F.B.; Speed, J.J.
      - February 21, 1854 - March 11, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 4)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines; House Line.
        March 5, 1854. describing a journey west, and plans for the farm in Ithaca.
        Indianapolis.
        Cornell, Franklin C.; Wood, Phebe; Cornell, John H.; Cornell, Mary Ann.
      - March 12, 1854 - March 26, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 5)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines, transfer of lines; legal suits.
        March 19, 1854. Mary Ann Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "?I most sincerely hope that you will finally succeed in geting together enough of this worlds goods so that you can finally make up yuir mind to settle down on some nice spot and enjoy the comforts of 'home sweet home' with your family. Oh, how happy I should be if it could be so, my dear little do you know the many lonely hours I have passed in your twelve years of absence from home, the cares and anxieties of home all resting on me and the still more anxious care for one I loved dearer than life itself?"
        March 24, 1854. Amos Kendall to Ezra Cornell:
        "I regret to learn that you and Mr. Wade do not get along amiably. These quarrels kill the telegraph; and no sooner is one quieted than another springs up."
        March 26, 1854. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "I rejoice that the Great State of N.Y. has granted her sons at last the justice, though tardy, of a prohibitory liquor law; it will save the rising generation if it does not rescue those who are already on the?plain of inebriacy."
        Ithaca; Indiana.
        Cornell, E.B.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Kendall, Amos; Speed J.J.
      - March 27, 1854 - April 12, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 6)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines, patent rights, transfer of patents.
        April 9, 1854. from Chicago, describing conditions aboard a crowded train, and the benefits of wholesome air.
        Michigan; Indiana.
        Wood, Phebe; Kendall, Amos; Cornell, Ellen.
      - April 13, 1854 - April 22, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 7)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines, transfer of lines and stock.
      - April 23, 1854 - May 20, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 8)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines, transfer of lines and stock; Speed's unapproved sale of telegraph stock and lines.
        Speed, J.J.; Kendall, Amos; Cambridge, Livingston.
      - May 21, 1854 - May 30, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 9)
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Wood, M.B.; Speed, J.J.
      - June 1, 1854 - June 9, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 10)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines; Speed's unapproved sale of telegraph stock and lines.
        June 1, 1854. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "This act of perfidy of Speed & W[ade] will lead to new combinations, whether the plans they had formed will all mature, or whether the frosts of treachery may not nip some of them in the bud remains to be seen, I should not be surprised if the latter was the fact."
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Speed, J.J.
      - June 10, 1854 - June 23, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 11)
        Wood, Otis E.; Cornell, E.S.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Read, James H.
      - June 25, 1854 - July 8, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 12)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, western lines; Speed's unapproved sale of telegraph stock and lines; Erie & Michigan Telegraph Company.
        June 27, 1854. Amos Kendall to Ezra Cornell:
        "I am disposed to act with you in carrying out, as far as we can, the arrangements of June 1853 and in punishing the conspirators by whom both you and my principal [S.F.B. Morse] have been betrayed and defrauded."
        Kendall, Amos; Read, James H.
      - July 11, 1854 - July 26, 1854 (Box 15, Folder 13)
        July 18, 1854. J.J. Speed to J.H. Wade concerning the sale of western lines.
        Read, James H.; Speed, J.J.; Wade, J.H.
      - July 27, 1854 - August 15, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 1)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, pipelayer and underground telegraph, office operations; Ezra Cornell's ill health and treatment.
        July 27, 1854. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell from Detroit concerning underground telegraph, family news and health, and instructions to Ellen on the care of the children in Ezra and Mary Ann's absence.
        Detroit; Ithaca; Logansport, In.; Indiana.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Cobb, Emory.
      - August 16, 1854 - August 31, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 2)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, finances, consolidation of companies, Ohio, Indiana & Illinois line.
        August 20, 1854. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann from Indianapolis reporting on his health and discussing the treatment received for his condition.
        August 27, 1854. Ezra Cornell, Mary Emily Cornell, Mary C. Robertson and M.B. Wood to Mary Ann Cornell from Albion sharing family news.
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Curtiss, George; Pew, W.P.; Robertson, Mary C.; Wood, M.B.; Cornell, Mary Emily.
      - September 1, 1854 - September 7, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 3)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, finances; Erie & Michigan Telegraph Company; cholera.
        September 2, 1854. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann from Detroit:
        "It is very sickly about Albion for such as have defective constitutions or shattered health, and many deaths have occurred?"
        Family news.
        September 3, 1854. Amos Kendall to Ezra Cornell reporting on telegraph business in New York and possible consolidation of lines.
        Detroit; Albion.
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Kendall, Amos; Cornell, Molly; Cornell, Alonzo B.
      - September 8, 1854 - September 17, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 4)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, stocks, office operations, business conflicts with House and Wade, consolidation of lines.
        September 8, 1854. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann from Michigan City:
        "Speed and Wades effort at my distruction by their diabolical sale to the enemy has proved a signal failure on their part, and will produce them a harvest of curses from the verry men who were to reap the golden apple of their treachery."
        Ezra Cornell's health, telegraph business, and reflections upon his persevering and succeeding in the business despite Mary Ann's father's advice to pursue other things.
        Indianapolis; Wisconsin; Indiana.
        Smith, F.O.J.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Speed, J.J.; Tillotson, D.T.; Pew, W.P.
      - September 18, 1854 - September 29, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 5)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, finances.
        September 22, 1854. E.B. Sadler to Ezra Cornell concerning F.O.J. Smith's claims.
        September 24, 1854. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann from Michigan City:
        "I wish you was here with me, I am not as well used when alone as when you are with me, I dont get as good a room, nor as clean a bed, I dont get called to my meals as early or by as pleasant a messenger, and at table I have to wate longer before being wated upon. All those ills are incident to being alone every one of which would banish before the magic presence of a woman.".
        Attempts to persuade Mary Ann and Emma to join him and discussion of the advantages of traveling during the winter.
        Michigan; Indiana; Ohio.
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Pew, W.P.; Livingston, Cambridge; Cornell, John H.; Sadler, E.B.; Haviland, J.
      - September 30, 1854 - October 19, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 6)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois line, finances, new western lines.
        October 6, 1854. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann from Chicago concerning family news from Michigan, telegraph business, and New York politics with reference to "fusion."
        Indiana; Ohio; Illinois.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Pew, W.P.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Tillotson, D.T.; Hopkins, P.A.; Faxton, Theodore.
      - October 20, 1854 - November 2, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 7)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, Ohio, Indiana & Illinois line, finances.
        October, 20, 1854. George Curtiss of the New York, Albany and Buffalo Telegraph Company to Ezra Cornell requesting that a meeting be held to discuss a permanent Western connection.
        Curtiss, George; Speed, J.J.; Pew, W.P.; Cornell, D.B.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Hopkins, P.A.
      - November 3, 1854 - November 15, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 8)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, Erie & Michigan line, finances; Southern Michigan Telegraph Company.
        Utica; Indiana.
        Pew, W.P.; Cornell, D.B.; Haviland, J.; Curtiss, George; Faxton, Theodore; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Caton, J.D.
      - November 16, 1854 - November 24, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 9)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, finances, stock purchases.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, D.B.; Skinner, G.W.; Curtiss, George.
      - November 25, 1854 - December 12, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 10)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, finances; House Company.
        Montreal; Ithaca.
        Cobb, Emory; Wood, O.S.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cornell, D.B.
      - December 14, 1854 - December 26, 1854 (Box 16, Folder 11)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, stock, office operations, consolidation of lines; Erie & Michigan Telegraph Company; House Company.
        December 14, 1854. Alonzo B. Cornell to Ezra Cornell discussing finances and Ithaca real estate holdings.
        December 15, 1854. Amos Kendall to Ezra Cornell concerning telegraph business and the actions of the House people.
        December 17, 1854. Franklin C. Cornell to Ezra Cornell:
        "I am going to school this winter to try to finish my education so that I can be of some help to you. Next time you write to me I want you to tell me what you want me to go at in the spring for I want to begin to make some calculation on it."
        Indianapolis; Ithaca; Detroit.
        Cornell, Alonzo B.; Pew, W.P.; Kendall, Amos; Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Franklin C.; Curtiss, George; Haas, J.; Cornell, D.B.; Cornell, John H.
      - December 30, 1854 - January 17, 1855 (Box 16, Folder 12)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, finances, Erie & Michigan line, stock, Southern Michigan line; House Company.
        Albion; Ithaca; Albany; Boston.
        Cornell, D.B.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Cobb, Emory; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Kendall, Amos; Cornell, Mary Ann; Curtiss, George; Cornell, John H.; Wade, J.H.; Haas, J.; Hopkins, P.A.
      - January 18, 1855 - January 30, 1855 (Box 16, Folder 13)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, finances, Cleveland, Wheeling and Zanesville line, Ezra Cornell's settlement with Speed, stocks; House Company.
        January 21, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "Speed evident regrets his treachery toards me and proffers his services, to aid me in any way that I can suggest and at any time that his services can be available. I rarely get cheated twice by the same person."
        January 30, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Franklin C. Cornell:
        "I hope if you decide to go to school that you will make up your mind to spend your time profitably, remember that knowledge is power."
        Albion; Utica.
        Haas, J.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Curtiss, George; Hopkins, P.A.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Chace, Rebecca; Pew, W.P.; Cornell, Franklin C.
      - January 31, 1855 - February 16, 1855 (Box 16, Folder 14)
        Telegraph business correspondence: Erie & Michigan line, finances, Ohio, Indiana & Illinois line, Southern Michigan line, western lines, office operations; House Company.
        Albion; Ithaca.
        Cornell, Franklin C.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Elwood, Isaac R.; Kendall, Amos; Wood, O.S.; Draper, J.S.
      - February 19, 1855 - March 21, 1855 (Box 17, Folder 1)
        Telegraph business correspondence: office operations, western lines; Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois Telegraph Company.
        March 10, 1855. from Albion:
        "Last saturday one of the cars got thrown off the track in which was four of my men, one of them was so injured that he died yesterday. He leaves a wife, who will soon have an heir."
        March 15, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "Tell mother & Emma that I look at their daguerratype frequently and think it is the prettyest picture."
        March 17, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "?it was a California show, going to California, a panorama of an over land trip to California where you can 'see the Eliphant for two dimes'?"
        Michigan.
        Wood, M.B.; Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, Alonzo B.
      - March 22, 1855 - April 10, 1855 (Box 17, Folder 2)
        Telegraph business correspondence: refinancing of stock, office operations, western lines, Ely judgment; Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois Telegraph Company; smallpox.
        March 31, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Alonzo B. Cornell:
        "?I have a sharp corner to work out of, that Ely judgment is 3471.88. I have got permission to draw on Mr. Chester for $2,500?"
        Indiana; Ithaca.
        Beebe, Jeremiah S.; Cornell, D.B.; Wells, Henry.
      - April 11, 1855 - May 1, 1855 (Box 17, Folder 3)
        Telegraph business correspondence: refinancing of stock, office operations, western lines, Ely judgment; Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois Telegraph Company; Erie & Michigan Telegraph Company; smallpox.
        April 12, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "He may escape as there is not one in twenty who have been vaccinated that take the small-pox on exposure."
        April 22, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "Calista was on her way to Windsor Canada to teach in a school of fugitives. They are sent to Canada as teachers by some society who have the educational welfare of the blacks in Canada under their keeping."
        April 29, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "I see a lot of boys in front of my window gambling with pennies. I hope my boy Perry is better engaged."
        Ithaca; Michigan.
        Speed, J.J.; Cornell, Mary Ann.
      - May 2, 1855 - May 12, 1855 (Box 17, Folder 4)
        Telegraph business correspondence: refinancing of stock, office operations, western lines, Morse telegraph patent; transfer of lines; Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois Telegraph Company; Erie & Michigan Telegraph Company; Southern Michigan Telegraph Company; House Company; smallpox.
        Kendall, Amos; Chester, E.W.; Hopkins, P.A.; Cornell, E.B.
      - May 13, 1855 - May 31, 1855 (Box 17, Folder 5)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, transfer of lines, western lines, office operations; Southern Michigan Telegraph Company.
        May 13, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "Homeopathy seems to do verry well when there is nothing the matter. It is so nice to take but when I am sick it seems to require the old ugly doses of the 'old butchers' to cure me."
        Wood, O.S.; Wood, M.B.; Faxton, Theodore; Smith, F.O.J.
      - June 2, 1855 - June 22, 1855 (Box 17, Folder 6)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, transfer of lines, western lines; Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois Telegraph Company.
        June 7, 1855. Mary Ann Cornell to Ezra Cornell describing unsatisfactory family conditions in Ithaca:
        "I wish if money is plenty at the west that you would send me some, as Alonzo is so hard up that I can't get any of him, and I can't well get along without some?I think Ithaca will not hold me long if they go west to live, if your business keeps you there, there is nothing in Ithaca worth living for, and I wish you would sell everything you own here?but if you do come here and try living as I have this thirteen years and then you would be able to judge something about it."
        June 10, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "I will pay your expenses out, that is to say, if you can get some body to advance your expenses out I will refund the money."
        June 15, 1855. Ezra Cornell to Mary Ann Cornell:
        "The next great question of the Day is the Know Nothing convention at Phil. that is of great political moment, not because of its Hindooism but because there is some hundreds of ordinarily inteligent men from all sections of the country and they may be persueded to reflect to some extent the feeling of their several communities feelings on the great issue of the day, liberty, or slavery. The Telegraph announces a split in the convention on that question -- this is a favourable sign, it shows that the concience of the north is being quickened, and may be regarded as the death knell to Southern Slave drivers, and Northern dough faces."
        Cornell, Mary Ann; Cornell, E.S.; Cornell, Alonzo B.; Wells, Henry; Curtiss, George.
      - June 24, 1855 - July 10, 1855 (Box 17, Folder 7)
        Telegraph business correspondence: finances, office operations, transfer of lines, western lines, stock payments due; Ohio, Indiana, and Illinois Telegraph Company; Southern Michigan Telegraph Company; Erie & Michigan Telegraph Company; Ezra Cornell's broken arm.
        July 7, 1855. Ezra Cornell to E.W. Chester describing his railway accident in which his arm was broken and mutilated.